[Music]
start with two real numbers theta less
than phi both less than pi over two
on the domain from 0 to pi over 2
graph the functions y equals the tangent
of x which is concave up and increasing
and the function y equals sine of x
which is concave down and increasing on
the domain
secant line connecting the origin to the
point theta sine of theta
has the equation y equals the sine of
theta over theta times x and this secant
line lies above sine of x for x larger
than theta similarly the secant line
connecting the origin to theta tangent
of theta has the equation y equals the
tangent of theta over theta times x and
this secant line lies below the tangent
function
if we plug phi into the sine function we
see that we have sine of phi
and this is less than what happens when
we plug phi into the secant line
which is the sine of theta over theta
times phi
likewise if we plug fee into the secant
line of the tangent function
we get a value of tangent theta over
theta times phi
and that must be less than what happens
when we plug phi into the tangent
function
which gives us tangent of phi
[Music]
we can divide the first inequality by
the positive value sine of theta
resulting in sine of phi over sine of
theta is less than v over theta and we
can divide the second inequality by
tangent of theta
resulting in phi over theta is less than
tangent of phi over tangent of theta
but then we can string these two
inequalities together
and we see that sine of phi over sine of
theta is less than phi over theta which
is less than tangent to phi over tangent
of theta
this is known as aristarchus's
inequalities
[Music]